Yeah, it's a great honor to be here and
like Don said, I'm actually one of our
own. I graduated uh I did my PhD uh
between 2009 and 2013. Uh before AI and
deep learning and things were cool or
basically handing out in SDH uh if you
if some of you are have visited bears
and we didn't really have that fancy
building back then uh still getting food
uh on nuclear and things like that. Um I
think you know like it's probably good
to basically just talk a little bit
about like who's this dude what is his
thought process and things like that
right and back at Berkeley days and then
my first job back at Google I was a
researcher looking into AI uh like AI
modules and things like that and one of
the things that we did back at Google
was Google net or what we call inception
as one of the leading image recognition
models um and and then I realized I
wasn't really a good researcher uh but
I'm uh slightly good at writing code um
started writing uh um AI frameworks such
as cafe and later particip participated
in in tensorflow and ptori and things
like that. And the one thing that we
kind of found was that with all those AI
algorithms evolving uh we start seeing
very much different patterns from the
conventional computer science whether it
be microservices or databases or data
analytics and things like that. And uh
and of course for quite a lot of these
system designs to change for us to build
newer larger and more you know like uh
real real world scale kind of
applications. Um and so basically
started basically like going from
research into engineering and then after
many years started a company called
leptin AI trying to basically build a
cloud kind of infrastructure that fits
the AI workload especially for LM
training and different things like that.
uh we got acquired by Nvidia. So
basically still peppery back in back in
the big company environment and um and
so I kind of feel that like I don't
really have very deep knowledge about
the state-of-the-art research part of AI
but hopefully the experience taught me a
little bit about you know stories on the
road. What kind of things people are
caring about in the industry right now?
What kind of you know like what kind of
uh uh cost benefits ratio analysis and
things like that are people thinking
about when they are doing a startup and
model and applications and things like
that. I would like to basically share
that with you guys. Um I kind of want to
always start with a kind of more not
scientific but interesting thought
process.
We've seen quite a lot of people talking
about the term AGI
and basically saying hey there there's
this mysterious model that seems to be
able to understand everything and it's
getting smarter and smarter. Now,
there's no question that they're getting
smarter, right? But are they so
mysteriously good or are they actually
been built with some really simple
principles that we've kind of learned
in, you know, like CS281 or things like
that?
And so I grew up in China. Uh my home
language is Chinese. And so we've all
typed, you know, on keyboards type in
English. It's very simple, right? It's
what you see is what you get. You type A
and then on the screen you show A. Now,
if you have a bit of knowledge about
Chinese text, sorry. Yeah.
Okay.
It's kind of weird. The the mouse isn't
I just put it over there or I can
minimize it. Let's let's just put it
there. It normally wouldn't have too
much sense. So um so basically if if you
if you have seen all those like Chinese
logos and things like that you know that
Chinese characters don't really show up
on the keyboard right it's an indirect
typing kind of process where the
character is different from the querty
keyboard so what you see isn't really
what you got in the old days people
solve that problem by having literally a
Chinese keyboard with individual keys as
you know metal foundaries somewhere up
So, the way you do it is you move around
that keyboard. You find a key out of
something around 3,000 to 5,000 common
characters. You click that thing and
there's a mechanical structure that gets
that that foundry up clicks onto that
row and then when you release it, it
comes back and you find the next key. A
huge keyboard. Now um over our you know
early computer science days we've known
how to type 26 keys and so on but
imagine how do we deal with that and the
other question is you know we're typing
sentences moving these kind of like
handle around is hugely difficult right
how do we actually make sure that things
are more efficient when we actually
typing of course today we don't use
these kind of keyboards all those
Chinese students are still typing on for
the keyboard but this is how things
started
Well, the fundamental question of the
same logic as when you are basically
saying like how do you actually seek to
the next block of data on your spinning
key uh hard drive and things like that.
The idea is that the distance between
the current character and the next
character matters a lot, right? If your
last character is on the top and then
you want to type the next character of
your phrase down there, then you're kind
of, you know, in a in a bad position
because you have to move quite a lot.
Which is why in the old days if you use
Windows and things like that in a in a
spinning hard drive there is things
called def fragmentation and things like
that making sure that since that the
same file stays in the same I forgot
even that word like stays in the same
part nearby part of the of the hard
disk. So then people started becoming
smart. I mean that was basically in the
1920s and 1930s and people are like how
do we actually group things together so
that we can minimize the movement of my
handle. They went out to libraries they
started counting they started counting
what we call today bgrams and engrams
and things like that. basically saying
okay given the previous characters or
given the uh
yeah kind of weird because like the the
mouse is not showing up
shall we just keep it over there
probably right probably that doesn't
block too much so so then we basically
start to counting those biograms and and
more and then we start to grouping
things together the words that are
basically like the characters that
happen together gets grouped together so
that things get more efficient. Now for
example here over there from the top to
bottom what what we see is chio which is
gas and yi which is paint right here
what we're seeing is jungo which is
China and then which is the Chinese
ethnical group and things like that and
by doing that people found that the
typing speed the typing speed comparing
to a random keyboard got massively
improved.
Now that was basically in the old days
we're like this is simple right you just
count and then you basically do
prediction of what would you would type
next in today's LLM vernacular
we call this thing with a uh more fancy
word called next token prediction right
we have a module we see what kind of
things are in front of it and then we
predict what is the next token uh there
were researches um to basically see
whether you can use the history or use
the surrounding part or the future to
predict the current word. Uh there was a
model called bird a few years ago which
is basically saying given the character
before it and after it how do we predict
the current word and the models that we
are using quite you know extensively
today called GPD models only use the
history kind of similar to when we are
typing something.
The difference is that in the old days
we're basically like doing all these
manually. So we cannot really go very
detailed. we can probably count two or
three characters before it. Conventional
NLP will actually kind of constrained by
these kind of constraints because you
can basically look at biograms and you
know like probably four or five gram is
probably the upper limit that you can go
because that correlation matrix gets you
know multi-dimensional crazy. Today we
can actually look into what we call the
context length right the uh start the
save models having normally millions of
tokens context length so you can look at
a lot of the previous context to predict
next token and as Ilia Saskke would say
that basically this is a mode of
compression compression compressing
compressing knowledge into prediction
next token and by doing that simple
action and producing that sequence then
you will be able to capture a lot of
implicit intelligence or things like
that. So a lot of these basic ideas kind
of come, you know, like in in similar
ways, of course, with more sophisticated
and powerful models
and and so so what I kind of like want
to basically like cover is four topics.
One is basically in this in the space of
LLM, what kind of algorithms are there?
What kind of models we're looking into?
Uh I'm not going to be diving into the
exact math because I'm a terrible
researcher. So I'm sure that there are
way smarter researchers who can
basically tell those. I'll just like
talk about it in from a outside in or
applicationdriven kind of approach and
the second is basically on top of these
models what kind of applications are out
there what kind of applications are
doing great if you want to build an
application what kind of parameters you
might think about and then we dive down
into the infrastructure side which is
really my comfort zone talking about you
know AI infra and why is it different
from the conventional cloud and things
like that because cloud has been around
for 20 years and why suddenly things are
changing a little
And in the end I kind of want to
basically talk a little bit about
hardware and stuff like that and see you
know like if uh we can find similar uh
like like analogies in the in the
conventional
hardware land and of course when we talk
about hardware this hardware is going
down and uh let's uh let's wait my my
apologies. We used to joke that you know
the the three hardest things in um two
hardest things in computer science is
printers and display. This is one of the
hard problems. All right. Seems to have
stabilized and uh and yeah well and
after after this I think you know like
if you like I can basically talk about
about the pain points of doing a startup
and things like that if you like. And of
course one uh mandatory disclaimer is
that since you know like we are I'm
currently employed in the company. All
these kind of opinions do not really
reflect the uh the opinion of the
company and uh it's more basically me
from an individual contributor and a and
a and and a and a kind like a dude with
too much code kind of perspective. All
right. So, um just uh just similar to
what we were just talking about, I mean
there is quite a lot of interesting
models that comes up and uh starting
from you know chatbt or even earlier
models that you might remember such as
chinchilla and palm from Google and
things like that. Uh GPD 3.5 really
started uh this trend of you know LM
frenzy. Um we've all been asking
ourselves every six months basically
saying hey are we actually plateaued?
Have we actually plateaued in the model
qualities? And it seems that even today
we haven't really seen a plateauing
effect and um the two streams of models
both closed ones and open source ones
are continuing to be having a very
healthy competition and um as of this
graph is actually a very nice Twitter
gentleman um from 2024 and uh in the
last you know couple months we've seen
really great um closour models such as
GPT5 Gro and Gemini Ki coming up and uh
in the open source land we've seen a
very quick change of thrones I would say
uh going from llama models to the models
such as deepseek quen or tiwin as in
Chinese and GPT open source from open
sour from open air itself as well. What
we are basically observing is that
closour models continue to ace in the in
the uh absolute quality and as we talk
to enterprise um clients or basically
partners out there such as you know say
the sales forces the Pinterest and
things like that people basically do
feel that open source model or closour
models actually leading in quality and
especially the newest cap capability of
doing reasoning and stuff like that but
the gap between open source models and
closed source models are becoming
smaller and smaller I would say in 2023
maybe the gap is around a year and more
than a year and today what we're
thinking about is something around six
months. So basically when there is you
know like new approaches coming out uh
normally open source models are able to
catch up really quickly in terms of
reasoning for example deepseek is
probably one of the um one of the first
papers that detailed the capability of
test time scaling and that actually you
know educated the whole community to
actually catch up really quickly.
Um,
and this the next questions people often
ask is like there's quite a bunch of
models and uh are we actually in the
land of a self-fulfilling prophecy and
we're only training models and not using
them right aka is there a bubble and I
tend to basically use some more
objective measurements in addition to
the news pieces from Techrunch and other
places of course really great news
pieces I tend to use basically more
objective usage statistics to look into
uh whether there's battle or not and
there's a very nice uh website or web
page called open router which aggregates
a lot of the models into more unified
API so that people can easily consume
those and uh a side effect or basically
a side result of that is basically it
will be able to look at the total
consumption at least from that channel
open router and also the distribution of
different kind of models and how how uh
popular they are and so starting from
2024 and even earlier and we can see
that the consumption of the models are
actually surging. So I remember about
you know like a year ago at that time
there was the consumption of something
around you know like uh 50 trillion uh
uh to something 60 uh uh sorry um 50
billion sorry 50 billion to 60 billion
tokens per day and today when you look
at it is something around uh 4.9
trillion so about 10x growth in the last
uh in the last year. Apparently we are
actually seeing a very solid use of
these models. An interesting thing is
that you can see there is a very a very
big battle actually between the open
source models and clos models. So uh the
graph here uh that chart here this shows
on September 15th what are the models
that are most popular and you can see
there Grock there's anthropic there's
Gemini the one so Noma sky alpha is
actually uh Gro 4 being tested in a
semi-secret fashion and uh the open
source models that we mentioned such as
deepseek and libit down there quen and
things like that are still being doing
pretty well. uh there is also a uh a a
ranking by application areas and
different applications. So uh this is
really a good place if you're interested
in diving into more data science and
analytics of the dynamics of the
different models. So apparently there's
a continued growth of consumption which
actually gives us hope that you know AI
this round has actually been very
helpful
and and so if we look at the more
researchy side of the world this is my
personal understanding not completely
right about why there are new things
that continue continuously excites us
and some of the ideas as an old dude I
kind of tend to basically tie it back to
uh to the other research topics or
research ideas in the ML uh community.
So in 2022 basically we started knowing
about GPT and it's kind of similar to I
would say Alexand about you know um 13
years ago because this is really a
structural innovation or change that
fundamentally improved the quality in
this case the text understanding and
back in Alexand days it freed computer
science researchers from using simple
handcrafted features such as you know
sift and pyramid kernels to a more
principle deep learning approach. Now as
we saw TBT taken on very well and people
are doing structure tuning and things
like that and we when we believe that
the model might be just the towing then
a mixture of experts came out. Uh the
idea is that you can actually use a
massively sparse model and sparsely
activate a model to improve the
efficiency and uh decrease the model
size while actually um maintaining a
pretty good quality. This kind of things
happened in the past as well. And uh if
you think about you know like very early
Beijian learning kind of things ensemble
with very simple classifiers worked
really well. And uh in the convolutional
neuronet days uh the Google net paper or
the inception paper exactly kind of like
adopted a similar approach by having not
one big chunky network but you know like
sparsely uh well actually in that case
it is like still sparsely parameter but
always active different paths um in each
inception unit to achieve a much better
um parameter utilization. um you can
also kind of derive things from the
theory of tensity composition and things
like that but that's a bit too
theoretical and I'll refrain from diving
deep into that now these are all
structural changes and then when we feel
that you know structure funing and
things like that using a very simple lo
function to basically train a model has
plateaued then in 2024 we found and
openai's u blog post actually um said a
very interesting theory which is like
you can actually start using test time
scaling or basically have the model
mumble longer in some way during testing
time and having it reflect on its
intermediate results to get a better
result. This kind of is you know similar
I I try to basically draw some
analogies. It kind of similar to the
idea of you know like say multi-
instance learning or basically fully
convolution neuronet by back in the days
by doing prediction
multiple times across the uh uh the
space domain and try to get a better
results. In this case it's basically
doing prediction along a much better
time domain and accumulate and reflect
on the intermediate guesses that you can
have and get a better result. Now, um
there is debates about whether test time
scaling is kind of the last leg for us
to squeeze out a bit of the uh the the
the intelligence out of an existing
model and things like that and people
are a little bit pessimistic about it.
And I think one thing that really kind
of made people much much more interested
in the model innovation is the uh
massive application of reinforcement
learning. Uh Deepseek was actually one
of the early papers talking about that.
But we know that OpenAI has been using
this to train our models for a long
time. I think one thing that really
excites me personally is that
reinforcement learning allows us to
actually define in a more principled way
a much more sophisticated loss function
because before that the idea is you know
like we have a bunch of sequences and
then I use the next token as the the the
loss function the the objective to train
the models it's not really exactly tied
to the end result reinforcement allows
us to basically say a model should
basically do some rollout or prediction
s and then look at the long-term
look look at you know the end of the
horizon and then you know provide
feedback about the quality of the end
result right um fundamentally it's
basically saying it's difficult to
define a loss function that is actually
ma matching the the thing that we want
to do but RL allows us to have a
principled way to do it RL ties back to
really old days of robotics and things
like that I think you know if you're in
ex department I think the prelim
examination still requires you to read
that big satanto book which is
interesting because It has a great
comeback over the years and uh and so
basically if you look at the modules and
things like well if you look at the hype
cycle of of Garner which is one thing
that you know um in industrial
participants like me would normally look
at you can see that a lot of the ideas
are very quickly iterating and evolving.
Um if you look at model ops and then rag
retrieval augmented generation and
things like that has only been out for
around uh a year or two but it's it's
already been kind of like like like it
had its days and it's coming down and
then right now what we are looking at
this prompt engineering agentic AI and
stuff like that are becoming more and
more important this ties to a very
interesting question which is like in
these kind of days how do we actually
think about building applications on
topic because you know you might have uh
Remember that rag or basically like
search augmented
chatbot and things like that used to be
a big thing. It continues to be but it
seems that now everyone's talking about
agents. So how do I actually think about
applications and how do we actually
build applications and things like that.
So back in the the leptton days we were
doing a infra and unavoidably we'll have
to look into what kind of applications
people are building so that we can serve
them well and one observation that we
have is there are normally two types of
applications. One's a consumer apps and
one is basically business services or
enterprise services and things like
that. Today what we see is a thriving
number of consumer applications because
the models are indeed very smart and are
actually able to you know like foster a
lot of innovative creativity,
entertainment and productivity and
things like that. Business applications
or enterprise applications have a very
strong potential to actually make you
know billion dollar businesses but as as
we all know businesses move kind of
slowly and things like that. So we are
only seeing the emergence of that. Let
me give you some examples. So basically
we were basically thinking how hard is
to make an an application, right? That's
an that's an API and and and uh and what
is the distance between an API and then
something that's useful. So this story I
want to basically like tell you this
story which literally happened within
like some of our engineers and I was
basically chatting with a gentleman
called Yadon who's in Singapore and over
Chinese New Year he was like I'm so
bored. this is Chinese New Year and uh
other than my grandparent or my parents
actually like forcing me to have a kid.
I don't have no other topics to talk
about. I was like let me build an app
and so what one thing we were thinking
about this there are so many blog posts
and things like that and it's really
difficult for us to consume the massive
amount of information that's feeding
into our browsers and it was like how
easy could it be if we could have a bot
that lives next to our browser and helps
us basically do digestions analysis and
things like that. So over two days
basically he was a very smart front end
engineer over two days he built an app
which lives still today and uh so I'm
I'll show you how it works. So let's say
we have Berkeley's homepage um opened
and I'm too hasty to understand what
Berkeley is. So I basically say uh this
app little app basically Elmo say please
summarize for me and it goes like a
person reads the web page and it gives
my me the summarizations and things like
that says Berkeley is a lead in public
research university known for its
groundbreaking research top rank
academic programs and vibrant student uh
life that contributes to better world
and things like that and I can basically
ask questions like when is sorry um when
is Berkeley
founded hopefully it answers me
correctly Right? It's like 1868 which if
I if if I'm still correctly remembering
this right right so those kind of things
makes it really easy for us to build
something that wasn't possible before
and you might have heard about stories
like you know like a oneperson startup
and things like that this hasn't been a
startup yet but it shows that by
combining smart you know like an
application knowledge and basically like
other general programming skills and a
powerful LL model we'll be able to do
something that's way more efficient than
we could do before.
So a small cute application and there's
quite a lot of you know like much deeper
thoughts over there and coming along
this line of thought and if you look at
basically the consumer app landscape it
shows itself as a very highly fluid and
competitive land and horiz every half a
year basically puts out a report called
the top 50 generi web products and uh
and other kind of products and this is I
think August uh maybe September August
is 2025 and as you can see basically
there is quite a lot of applications out
there loosely speaking they get into a
few things that you can kind of like see
chat is one of the biggest topics so
chatbt gemini deep sea gro and things
like that um the other one is basically
coden is you like becoming much more uh
much more prominent and used by people
so you might have heard about cursor and
also like replet and things like that
there's also search that comes uh that
comes quite often so perplex lexity is
the most prominent one also started by a
Berkeley grad student um and uh and and
all these things are you know evolving
really quickly and uh and the landscape
shifts very quickly so this for example
is showing what's different from six
months ago and now
uh about that's that's 11 that are
basically like like that are just like
popped up into the top 50 in as short as
six months right and uh Gro and Quark
and and and and folks are actually like
in top 10. So so in this case you know
like um people are constantly asking
what is the what is the the mode because
people might think of some some some
models that are like the performing
really well but because of the
underlying LLM model doing really well
then in the end basically like very
quickly got surpassed by other
applications. One of the very prominent
example is a company called Jasper AI
which started in the chat tribute 3.5
days to be an editor helper or something
like that to help you basically do
content creation and things uh but for
better worse due to chatb models being
too good it started b having to pivot
into other areas we also see that models
such as basically like um I think 11
laps having its own you know model and
then mid journey having its own module
and knowing the the the customers really
well and been able to hold this mode
relatively well. But in general it's a
very it's a it's it's a blue it's it's
kind of like a blue ocean kind of field
and but there's quite a lot of
competitions over there
and and and one thing that we are we're
seeing is there's a lot of traffic but
who are willing to pay right and then in
all those consumer apps one trend a very
clear trend that we see is that if the
application actually targets proumers
aka they're still small consumers but
they are actually embedding those kind
of things into their daily work and
productivity. ity. It seems that people
are very much willing to pay and I'm
just cherrypicking a few uh succeeding
examples. Cursor as we all know is
basically embedded into quite a lot of
the coding practice that we have today.
Runway as a multimedia create creativity
and multimedia editing kind of tool has
been liked by a lot of the content
creators such as the Tik Tok guys and
also like people who are basically
starting shops on Etsy and things like
that. That's a very interesting hardware
kind of startup called ploud which
employs a very simple idea. I actually
have one here. So it basically have you
know like a credit card shaped kind of
you like recording device. Recording
device is not really new, right? It
basically it can basically like record
your conversations and things like that
and then connecting that to voice
recognition and GBT to tell you what are
the action items, what are the
conclusions, what are the main debating
points of the recorded meeting. uh which
is liked quite a lot by people who are
in the legal industry, in the consulting
industry and the healthcare industry and
things like that. 11 labs as we
mentioned has really awesome you know um
voice models and has been all of these
kind of guys are actually having you
like multiund million revenues and the
logic behind that is basically you know
like it seems that when things get into
productivity
you are very much willing to pay as a
consumer for example I play with uh
midjourney and then I was like hm I
really want to spend $ 20 $50 per month
just for fun and I was like no I'm not
going to do it but if this is basically
coding or basically if I'm a content
creator and I was like thinking about to
make sure that I can actually like do my
job much better am I willing to pay $20
and I was like of course I do and from a
startup guy perspective if you look at
every single person's you know it or
productiv productivity tool you will
find that it's not a lot of money so let
me count for a from a startup kind of
perspective when we have one new person
join in uh one new gentleman or lady
join in how much kind of s tools we
would set up for them. There's GitHub,
that's $20 or $25. There's Google
Workspace, $25. Slack, $12. One
password, $9, right? Get a copilot,
that's about $19 among a bunch of other
things. So, it's very easy for us to
basically for for people who are
actually like thinking about
productivity to shell out a couple
hundred dollars to, you know, support
doing a better job. And I think that's
basically one of the areas that the uh
that the smart startups are doing really
well over there. Still when we think
about enterprises things are in an
interesting position where a lot of the
enterprise applications are are growing
much faster than the more conventional
ones but not as fast as the you know
like the cursors and perplexities on the
consumer side. Um enterprise
applications have this unique barrier in
the sense that it just needs a lot of
work. So let me give you one example. Um
we all do search daily right we use
normally Google and in my own country by
and things like that. But the question
is what search engine do you use at
work? Maybe you're like doing internship
in in a company or things like that.
What kind of search engine do you use?
Normally I get two answers out of that.
One is well there isn't a good search
engine because all those things in like
wiki and jira tickets and things like
that just cannot be aggregated
and uh the other one is basically saying
we our company has our own internal
search tool but it kind of sucks because
it's just not high quality. uh there's a
startup called Glean which has it took a
little bit more than three years to
reach 100 million AR and quite a lot of
our friends in different companies
actually I was chatting with them was
like did you guys use clean and it was
like it's great it is the greatest
search engine enterprise search engine
that we have experienced the idea is
that it basically connects to the
multiple sources such as Google Drive
GitHub internal wiki and a bunch of
things Microsoft 365 and it will be able
to integrate all those authentications
and access control and things like that
to basically give every person a search
engine that is indexed on the set of
information that he or she is actually
able to access inside the company. Lots
of dirty work but addresses a very big
pain point of enterprises and it's
combining with AI then it's actually
doing pretty well. So I think you know
like basically when we think about the
potential of AI and answer the question
whether there's a bubble or not uh it's
still a lot of potentials especially
with the more nent enterprise market um
lyn is one and there are a bunch of
others such as sara who's basically
doing I think legal AI and things like
that and and if you go to like saya or
envision harvest reports you can see
quite a lot of like potential companies
over there um people basically started
normally by using closed source models
and build you know some of like end to
end kind of applications and then as
data start accumulating they started
basically like uh building their own
models and things like that. Uh there's
a constant debate whether the open AIS
and anthropics are actually going to be
taking over the world but uh in the in
in the industry we see things happening
differently. So there's a very
interesting uh app called Dualingo and
my kid actually use it to learn English.
which I don't know why they are actually
born here but they use they use that to
to learn English probably just to play
some games right Dualingo was actually
able to you know like people were like
oh wow when uh AI models are coming out
Dolingo is dead uh not so they're
actually living pretty well and what we
found is that Dualingo is actually able
to use AI models um open AI and things
like that I don't know what exactly they
use but they're able to use AI models to
start
creating content and more interactive
contents much more efficiently
And it creates this very complimentary
relationship where the better the AI
models are combining with the deep
knowledge of the customers and the you
know like the the language learning kind
of expertise that Dualingo has they
create a a one on one plus one larger
than two kind of effect and uh and it
basically boosts the quality of the
whole product and and and experience. So
I think this kind kind of basically like
is going to be continuing and we will
see very healthy synergy between the
model builder companies and also the
application companies.
Of course all those kind of things need
you know cloud infrastructure under
there to support the massive scaling. um
a very fresh off the boat kind of news
was like this morning I didn't know
about it ahead of time this morning u
media and open AI are announcing that
they are uh I think investing 100 100
billion or something like that into
computation infrastructure to build and
to scale the next generation models and
things like that which is basically the
massive scale that we're seeing in
infrasite and so in general I think
starting from uh even before CHBT maybe
like 2020s what we found is that AI
infra has become the the third pillar
the third pillar in the IT or cloud kind
of strategy no longer as a part or a
small part of you know like all those
cloud and IT but really becoming its own
sound and when I say the third pillar
what are the pillars that we're talking
about right um oh first of all what is
the need right the need is basically
like very very well um summarized by
professor Richard Sutton's u blog post
in 2019 he's basically saying the
biggest lesson that we have learned in
the 70 years of AI research Arch is that
we can employ a generalized approach
general method in today's context large
models deep learning models and things
like that and and we basically deploy a
large amount of computation numerical
computation onto a large amount of data
and that seems to be the most effective
way. So, so we need a large amount of
computation power
and if you look at the computation
history and a lot of the uh a lot of the
compute kind of idea actually came from
numerical computation in the 1970s we
know that scientific compute is a big
thing and on the on the hills of
Berkeley there is uh nersk right it's
basically uh built by the department of
energy and if you if you you have taken
or if you are taken the uh introduction
to parallel computers taught by
Professor James Demo and Kyle here. You
know that you know a lot of things that
are taught over there is about how do
you actually carry out large scale
matrix applications and things like that
and uh and those applications were
physics weather simulations and stuff
like that on a cluster with CPUs in the
back back in the days with good old
software such as Slimm and things like
that chugging along. And then um when
people want to basically like have
someone else to basically deal with the
computer and things like that, they
started the business of virtual private
servers. So that some companies data
centers and things can take care of the
physical machines and people build
applications on top and that eventually
rolled into what we know as cloud today
cloud services AWS, GCP and um and uh
Azure and and others. So, so we kind of
call it conventional cloud um in a sense
that they kind of started in the web
services days and what the need is
basically you know like we have we host
a bunch of machines we uh do
virtualizations on top of that we put a
bunch of microservices or uh small
workloads over there making it more
flexible um for people to not worry
about you know machine operations and
things like that and serving web
traffic.
Web service cloud grew for quite some
years and then when the idea of web 2.0
No, such an old idea. Uh, well, 2.0
came. There's a lot of idea about user
generated content and matching the the
the matching users content and the the
the consumer's interest, right? Tik Tok
and YouTube and things like that.
There's a lot of need for data
analytics. We uh record the user
activity data whether it be e e-commerce
or uh or you know like uh uh and content
cre or content consumption and things
like that. And we started building
recommendation engines and things like
that. And that actually required quite a
lot of data analytics. So around 2014
there are two interesting companies
coming out and one is called Snowflake
building the idea of cloud data
warehouse and the other one on the more
open source side came from Berkeley and
which is called data bricks on top of
spark and that set the idea of data
cloud where there is a massive amount of
data and massive distributed training uh
sorry distributed computation using SQL
and data analytics and things like that
and in 2020 when I actually started
doing AI we see that a lot of the
patterns are kind of different because
today we we actually call for quite a
lot of exoflops of float and even you
know like lower precision float
computations.
It has to be carried out with relatively
small amount of data but a lot of
compute and a lot of communication kind
of similar to the very old scientific
computation days.
And so so to kind of put things in more
abstract or basically like more more
principal terms, there are two
parameters that are governing the
thought of how we think about
infrastructure. One is data movement or
IO and the other one is numerical
computation or computation in the uh in
the old days in web compute there's
quite a lot of IO. We move data around
web pages you know images and things
like that. There's not too much of
compute because I just need to read
things off the disk and serve it to the
customers but lots of IO and a small
amount of compute and the workload looks
like microservices. It's embarrassing in
parallel. You have an a node.js server.
You replicate it if there's more traffic
and if you scale it down if there's no
traffic and then data compute is
slightly different in the sense that
still there's quite a lot of IO but the
computation is not that it's not that
embarrassingly parallel. you actually
have to use abstractions such as you
know like spark or basically map reduce
and things like that to carry out one
SQL as one big distributed system. SQL
gave you a very good abstraction but
under the hood you have to have a lot of
like complicated distributed scheduling
and things like that going on. AI is
kind of different in a sense that
compute is way bigger than IO. We also
we always talk about like large training
data sets and things like that but
that's normally still about you know
like say couple tens of terabytes or
maybe one or two pabytes or things like
that. Computers a lot training one
single image model is already one x of
flop. And uh we used to joke that if the
whole city of London everyone starts
using you know like their their pens to
to do calculations it takes them 4,000
years for the whole city of London to
train one model and in LLM today it's
even bigger
and uh and it's very distributed and in
the sense that for data for data infra
you can actually have some machines go
down and you just like redo the compute
of that chunk of compute on on the next
available map produced shard in AI
compute when you launch a distributed
training and If one of the GPU machines
go down, then it's the whole training
job is down for good, right? You better
basically like restart the whole job.
There's a bit of tolerance and things
like that. But if you look into the the
modern day distributed training, it's
not that easy. And that actually really
basically gives us the thought, hey, it
just looks like more like like MPI like
the old day slur kind of days, like the
old day scientific computation days. The
conventional cloud value proposition
that's originates from the web cloud
days no longer holds because
conventional cloud basically says I'm
going to be giving you an easier way to
acquire and install software. You can
basically say I can launch a cloud
database without having to install my
SQL myself and the other one is
basically cloud is basically say I'll
give you a a flexible supply chain by
having EC2 machines being pulled up and
released flexibly all the time. in the
AI world is kind of different in the
sense that if we list out there's not
too much applications in AI and there's
not too much variety it's pretty much
basically AI frameworks you know you
install back in the days PyTorch and
TensorFlow nowadays more popularly
PyTorch and then a few dependent
libraries on top of that such as
Megatron LM or lightning AI and things
like that so it's kind of simple there's
not too much variety of software the
workload is also quite unified in the
sense that there's a huge amount of
numerical computation for matrix
applications and things like that. Not
too much comput storage, network, big
data and things like that. It's simpler.
Supply chain wise is more rigid in a
sense that in conventional cloud you
have microservices that works really
well on virtualization and you can
actually migrate workloads between
different machines and things like that.
It's it's it's very nicely laid out in a
in AI cloud when you launch a large
training job with you know like say like
bunch of GPU machines then that machine
physically are just stuck together with
high performance networks and things
like that if one machine goes down you
need to move hold the whole thing you
shut down the whole thing and you find
another set of machine and you start
running things over there and um and for
for better or worse if you actually have
a bunch of CPU machines during the day
you're probably serving web traffic and
during the night you can repurpose it to
actually do data analytics and things
like that. Um, in the GPU land for
better or worse, uh, the workload is not
that interchangeable because it's really
good for numerical computation and you
cannot really run a web service on top
of GPU. So, interchangeability becomes
becomes harder
and that drives the emergence of what we
call the Neo cloud over the last few
years. Uh there's a very nice um like an
analyst kind of website called semi
analysis that I highly encourage you
guys to read if you're interested in
this land. Uh they coined up the term
neo cloud with the idea that you know
there are companies out there who can
actually focus on AI compute and AI
workloads aggregating GPUs and not
really worry about you know set up
database services and things like that.
The most prominent ones are basically
core weave uh lambda there's a European
one called NBS and a bunch of others.
they kind of start basically showing
their value by providing more more AI
ccentric um computation resources that
would you know reduce your cost improve
your availability and things like that
and of course you know the the
hyperscalers are also getting into this
field to create more AIcentric cloud
services.
The reason is that basically like um you
really cannot just get a bunch of GPUs
and and start running with it. Um I was
chatting with uh I was chatting with you
like one founder CEO um last year and he
was like man I'm spending so much time
curing GPUs and basically like
monitoring GPU host and things like that
which isn't good right uh there are
basically two choices up there one is
basically you know like uh you just have
an internal team that starts using Excel
or whatever to basically manage the
cluster and we did that back in the
Berkeley days I was the uh the assist
for our computer vision group and wasn't
really the choice. Um the captain
winners up there that I joke about
that's oral winners who basically lead
in Germany today and he was also one of
the poor systems back days. Uh the other
choices use Kubernetes. Now you you
might have heard quite a lot of sins
about Kubernetes being the best sin
since sliced bread. um AI researchers
don't seem to think so mainly because
Kubernetes is a very nice abstraction
but normally for S surres site
reliability engineers or operation
people and when you actually basically
provide you know like the Kubernetes
type abstraction to the AI researchers
they're like no I don't really know how
to think of you know parts deployments
parallelism completion and things like
that and as an AI researchers even if I
even after I did a startup I still don't
know those kind of things. Yeah.
Research is like I want a simple mindset
where I get four machines. I get MPI set
up and I run on this PyTorch job and I
just happily wait for the result. If one
of these kind of things go down, please
give me another four machines run the
same thing until things go wow. I don't
really want to deal with Kubernetes.
This is kind of like the fight today.
the holy war I would say between the
slurm researcher kind of mindset and the
kubernetes operations kind of mindset
which kind of like comes very often in
in in the community. Now the reason is
actually you know like uh the
fundamental problem of developer
efficiency and infra efficiency are just
in a conflicting state. Uh developers
want things to be really simple and
abstracted grow a job and get it done in
wise for better words GPUs do die today
actually. Uh the chart that you see here
is actually from a very nice analysis
from Facebook who are running their
cluster of I forgot how many machines
but you know probably at a scale of 100
thousand or something like that. they
find that you know like there's quite a
lot of reasons software bugs 40GPUs
memory issues and things like that and
and network issues that might cause the
machines to go down. So you do want some
sort of abstractions to uh hide these
kind of operational burdens away from
the uh from the developers and you know
get them a seemingly stable environment
for them to carry out their job and not
worrying about fixing GPUs 2 am in the
night
right so so we kind of basically we're
thinking about this I had to basically
use leptin as like a bullshitting kind
of marketing architecture but what we
found is that the best practices today
for a lot of the startup is four things.
One is basically to find a multiple
cloud supply chain because today GPUs
are still in short supply and uh and
normally when you want to basically find
2,000 GPUs to to train your model, maybe
your current provider doesn't have it
but the provider in the next state might
have it. So you basically want to figure
out how to actually uh smoothly migrate
your jobs between different clouds and
and of course since GPUs are so
expensive you want to basically make
sure that you are actually actively
looking at utilization and things like
that and not really just wasting idle
GPU hours. Uh normally people would
start looking for an AI native platform
that allows us allows them to basically
abstract away the Kubernetes jargon and
focus on the training jobs. a few really
good examples and I'll focus on the
Berkeley oriented ones right so we have
uh ray as an open source project a
couple of years ago actually maybe 10
years ago starting to basically serve
reinforce millennium before it's cool
and today as a general computation
framework there's a company called um
any scale that basically supports ray
and basically does commercializations
there's a very interesting uh new
project uh for a couple years now called
skyp pilot that allows people to find
efficient computation resources and then
basically like orchestrate workloads
across different clouds and things like
that. And essentially I think people can
actually piggyback on these kind of
frameworks and their platforms and then
build their own teams on model
applications because there's quite a lot
of things to be sorted out. taking uh
the the really famous um coding company
called Cursor for example, they will be
using you know standardized S services
to basically like to stabilize their
inference workloads and things like that
and focus their effort onto defining or
designing and training the next
generation coding models that would be
one of the key competition uh
competitiveness of of the company right
so those kind of things seems to be a
common best practice that we observe in
the uh in the industry
um lots of the things are kind of
different but in the end a lot of the
conventional wisdom of operating cluster
and operating services start basically
coming back. Uh I love to basically show
this picture because it shows that AI
infra is no different when it starts
becoming getting into products
basically. Um so so this is like one
Saturday afternoon in uh in like like
back in the startup days and then one of
our clients was basically running in a
large scale chatbot suddenly saw a uh
suddenly saw a uh a um a fluctuation of
their of our services and and when we
looked into it was a very classical
error that happened. Uh one of their
engineers accidentally shut off the main
model that they're serving on our
platform. And so of course everything
got idle. Well, what do you do then? You
restart it. Right now if you think about
it when you shut off a main service a
lot of the requests start basically
aggregating and waiting and you start a
multiple a service of multiple replicas.
What will happen is there's first
replica or first machine that pops up
and start accepting traffic. All those
crazy traffic start getting in there and
what happens that poor guy just dies.
Right? The second guy pops up with
what's going on and immediately he got
killed. And this is the typical thing
that often happens in a lot of the AWS
you know um like region well if region
fails and then it comes back normally
these kind of storms happen as well. So
we were like ah yeah we know about that.
So so Saturday afternoon we're basically
like sitting there together chatting
together with them was like okay let's
basically put you know like a
what is that called? um a traffic
regulator in front of the service so
that you know like we only allow a
certain amount of traffic coming in
gradually pushing the services up to
speed um in 15 minutes we're actually
able to recover the whole services but
we were like it's no different from
conventional cloud services so when we
are actually looking into basically
productization of these AI models all
these kind of conventional wisdom comes
and becomes helpful
all right so the last thing that I think
is like pretty interesting to talk about
especially Berkeley is that um we see
the hardware software designs to to come
back to a very interesting old way. So
in 1985 there was one of the very famous
you know supercomputers I guess that
came out uh which is called Cray 2. Uh
the computation power create 2 today um
is not really as big. was probably half
of an iPhone 5 back in the days was one
of these really beautiful mainframes. Uh
the thing that you are seeing is
basically the the the circular thing in
the front is the compute units hosting
the CPUs and the memory and things like
that. The the brown thing in the back is
that the cooling tower. It just deals
with cooling and stuff like that. Back
in the days, well, those kind of
mainframes have this beautiful idea that
there is one bus
and then you can attach different CPUs
and you can attach different memory and
storage on there and this whole thing
operates as if it is one single
computer. Really nice to do programming
really not that flexible. And then
during the cloud days, we were like
that's different. We shouldn't do that.
We should actually use small machines
and things like that. So um uh the thing
I'm showing on top there on the top
right part is uh a typical uh server
design by the open compute project OCP.
Uh OCP was created by a bunch of
industry participants like Facebook and
Google and things like that. And it
basically says I'm actually being able
to design really modular small machines.
each machine operates on its own and uh
and then I can basically shove it in
shove out individual machines really
well and um and then it serves
microservices and things like that
really well and then AI came and we feel
that we start needing to beef up the
machines. Today one of the most popular
service that we're using to run the uh
run the uh the the AM models is what we
call the DJX boxes. Um um both Nvidia
and AMD actually have in similar have
similar kind of setups for such boxes.
It's uh what we call a 4U um um rack
mountable unit which is about that tall.
It hosts eight GPUs and two CPUs and
it's a very beefy machine that is able
to run like deepse and GPUs models and
things like that becoming really bulky.
Uh but still it's a server it's a bigger
server in the internet days comparing to
the smaller internet CPU servers. And
then I think as of you know last year um
we started designing and in Nvidia's
term it's called ML72 basically rack
level um really nicely integrated um
servers set of servers that can do large
distributed training. So if you look at
that rack what happens basically the
middle part as you can see there's a bit
of like pattern difference over there.
The middle part are all switches um
highly connect or highly b high
bandwidth switches that allows the
machines to talk to each other and then
the top the ones on the top and the ones
on the bottom are basically you know
like a servers as as we normally have.
If you think about the cloud days, each
machine is its own, right? And machines
basically talk to each other by
primitives such as RPC or you know MPI
and things like that. But each machine
is its own domain. You cannot access as
a machine. You cannot access another
machine's memory without asking for
permission from it. In the MVL 72 and
similarly industry participants have
different kind of like setups over there
as well. The new pattern is that with
all those MV switches you will each
machine is actually able to directly
access other machines memory without
asking for permission. It operates very
much like a mainframe
with all those CPUs and GPUs being able
to access all those memory in that rack.
Um there's in the in the HPC world there
is like a very interesting pro project
called UPC universal parallel C by
providing abstraction of multiple
machines memory into one so that we do
not need to use primitives to ask for
permission to access each other's
memories and things like that. This is
exactly basically like achieving some
sort of that design. The benefit is if
you are training massive models or if
you're deploying massive models now you
no longer need to worry about chopping
the model into different pieces that can
fit into individual machines. You know
basically say hey put the model into
that big box or big rack and everyone
can access everyone's memory and things
like that. So a lot of the optimization
pieces that we think about such as
disagregated like prefilling and
decoding you know um uh uh procession
and things like that becomes much
easier.
This is still quite nent we haven't
really seen you like uh the the software
side like it and things like that fully
embracing that but we are seeing really
early already you know like explorations
of that. So VLM project, SG LM projects,
C Berkeley is great because all those
projects come from Berkeley. VLM sland
like we're actually like actively
looking into those and utilizing the
newest hardware innovations which seems
to be thinking about ideas back in the
mainframe days to actually push the
boundary of all.
Um I think AMDIA actually had a pretty
nice slide that I want to basically show
uh the evolution of the thoughts of the
scale right we basically started about
you know 1015 years ago by just using
GPUs as one additional card into my box
and then we started basically saying we
need more GPUs and today we need more
and more GPUs and we're thinking about a
rack level or basically a data center
level scaling of the models for training
and inference which is really nice. uh
there's an order of magnitude increase
in the computation needed and also the
corresponding memory needed and as one
example back in the days when we're
thinking about computer vision models
the state-of-the-art model such as
Google net was about 6 million
parameters and we're like that's a
fairly decent big model and today if you
think about LLMs an 8 billion parameter
model such as llama 8B is considered
small, very small, very small, but
computer vision models is three orders
of magnetic down there. And back in the
days, we thought it was big and so so
size is size really, you know, like like
we we we do see quite a lot of increase
in size and hence that actually drives
hardware innovations that drives back
the software innovation. Um I kind of
want to basically end the the the talk
by a very interesting application that I
actually did back in my uh back in my uh
back in my uh last last job as you know
like the big data and AI general manager
back at Alibaba um to show showcase how
difficult a real world like environment
might look like and how AI isn't really
able to solve all those problems. So so
so you know we were flying into and out
of different kind of airports. San
Francisco is a beautiful airport. If you
go to JFK or LX, you know that some of
the airports aren't the most convenient
ones. One of the biggest challenges of
all those airport operations is that
there's quite a lot of uh you know like
garbage time between a plane landing
onto the runway and basically like that
that that plane hits the tarmac. The
thought process is if you're in the air,
you don't care because you're watching
movies and things like that. The moment
you hit the ground, it's like I need to
get off the plane.
Same thing for passengers, same thing
for planes because planes want a faster
turnaround time so that they can be
useful, right? And uh and back in the
days this is done by you know manual ATC
personnels and things like that. And if
you uh if you read the news you know
that since the Reagan days uh there is a
growing shortage a continued shortage of
ATC personnel. And how do we solve that
problem? So back in the days I was
actually like participating in some of
the projects called like smart city or
smart airports to uh create a digital
twin of this airport by laying out the
map of the airport, laying out basically
the the all kinds of operational data of
the planes, their flights and things
like that and using computer vision and
sense to basically lay out the
positioning of different airports,
airplanes and things to analyze things
like where are the hot spot? are there
some sort of you know like taxi ways
that are actually blocking unknown to
ATC personnel blocking the traffic
efficiency and things like that and to
increase
nominally we we claim that was actually
able to increase the efficiency of the
of the airport operations significantly
and personally and off the record and I
I still find some of the airport that we
could we worked on highly congested so
it may or may not be useful but if you
think about it these are the real world
challenges that we're facing not only
basically saying, "Hey, here's the
prompt and please give me a text telling
me what I should do, but really to
connect data sources that aren't aren't
text and then basically create actions
that are not text either, right? There's
a lot of, you know, like new innovations
such as physical AI and things like
that, robotics and stuff going on.
Professor FA Lee from Stanford for
example is having a company called World
Lab that basically like like looks into
these kind of areas. So I think there's
quite a lot of like real world problems
that are that are expanding beyond LLMs
and uh and there is a massive amount of
opportunity that we could uh we could
unleash in this round of AI bubble and I
don't think it's a bubble in this round
of AI innovation uh to um to create the
next I guess industrial revolution. So
I'll stop here and I think you know some
of hopefully some of the materials will
be like interesting to you and um happy
to take questions if you have centric
kind of world how do how does business
model evolved to be competitive right
something like that so I think basically
the conventional model of hyperscalers
uh me working in one in the past is
often basically selling compute and then
sell the operational expertise or
basically the operational
like like simplicity to customers and uh
and today with LLMs I think it becomes
even more simple right so so
hyperscalers are I think they are having
a mindset shift um from selling
resources to more selling workloads or
results or tokens or something like that
uh they do have a unique advantage in
the sense that the the pool of computers
big and they themselves actually consume
a large amount of uh a a large amount of
AI compute as well because internally
when they train their models or
basically they run batch compute or
things like that uh that creates a bunch
of compute uh compute need that can be
basically plugged into the tidal wave of
inference need that unavoidably comes
when at a large scale right so I think
basically like hyperscalers would
continue to uh have a very advantage uh
in increasing the efficiency of the
underlying GPU operations
A few hurdles today still haunts the
field. For example, today a lot of the
training algorithms aren't really
designed to be to be kind of
interruptable.
Back in the days, I think you know if
you if if you read Google's board paper,
there's a very nice practice inside
Google engineering saying that you uh
you want to build your your your
workload to be interruptable and you
know item potent meaning that you can
rerun it, right? AI is such a nent and
hot field that a lot of the researchers
me included are just a bit spoiled
because we can just hog resources and
and efficiency. We don't care too much
about that. But I think as we get more
and more mature in the engineering
operations and care more about the
efficiency and productivity uh balance
then hyperscalers would actually
naturally use their scale as an
advantage to uh to to continue winning.
How how do we think the the economy of
of token cost versus price, right? So a
lot of the uh uh inference basically
like um although there is you know like
they are actually charging a price the
cost of serving those tokens is actually
still higher than than the uh than than
the cost or in other words like some of
the uh some of the application companies
when they are charging their customers
and then what they're paying the token
or model providers the fee they pay the
model providers are actually like higher
than the fee they collect from the
users. Right? This is indeed like a real
question.
I think there's one gentleman who
actually wrote it
current um the uh coding bot models.
They're basically saying coding bots
when they are selling seats is actually
um a glorified version of insurance and
insurance basically is built on the
assumption that people would consume
less, right? Or basically saying like if
someone sells you car insurance, they
assume that you don't get into
accidents. you don't want to maximize
your accident count and uh and as a
result the math or the economy the the
the economy analysis seems to be not not
adding up today. Uh I used to have kind
of similar thought as well when I was
doing a startup. One of the things that
we care quite a lot because we are in
for people is we look at cost and one
thing I kind of start you know realizing
is that when the industry is going
pretty quickly there is I would
basically say uh unavoidably or actually
in a better way uh waste or basically
like like a money losing kind of
mechanism. Uh Silicon Valley is probably
the only place where people are
investors are willing to basically
believe in a random dude, a random
technical dude coming up and basically
they have this brilliant idea that's
going to be losing money for many years,
but it will be creating value. Um and
give them money to to do a startup. Um
the the I think I think the logic is
that cost is never going to be a thing
in the long term uh run of things. For
example, um today GPT5 or GPT 4.40 40
and things like that are something
something around the the price of GPT3.5
a couple years ago but the quality is
much better. So I guess the the more
slow equivalent would actually apply to
the tokconomics as well in the sense
that you know like um if I am only
losing 50% of the money then next year
with the same quality I'll be breaking
even as long as customers are happy and
we're creating value. So I think a lot
of the companies in value are actually
built on this belief that we focus more
on creating the value and worry less
about burning money. Um of course this
is actually one structural risk that you
know like if there's no value then this
whole thing is a house of cards. Uh but
it seems that right now we see tractions
in you know search productivity coding
and things like that. So I would be more
optimistic.
Thanks
talk. I kind of casually mentioned that
rag is kind of like falling out of favor
um and there's new cool terms like
agentic AI coming in but it seems that
um rag is still very useful because we
cannot put all the information into a
terribly long context and uh and get an
accurate result out right yeah I fully
agree actually um this is one of the
interesting part you know like in a
startup land where uh there are new
concepts coming in every day and then
you know like um um there's a natural
tendency especially on Twitter for
better or worse to chase the newest
concepts wipe coding for example right
and uh and you're right basically uh uh
I think what I observe is that rack or a
good search algorithm is actually hugely
important for us to get accurate
information I was actually um it was it
was it was it was my anniversary
basically I was basically asking openai
I was like well would you like could you
actually recommend me a few you know
wine selections for celebration right
and what one thing I found is that it
started using web search and things like
that under the hood combined with LLM.
So I think you know like rag is not
really falling out of favor but has been
understood or basically like adopted in
a more in a more implicit way kind of
similar to no one talks about databases
today but we all use databases so I
think it's kind like it's getting mature
and there are other terms who are
basically like still in a very vibe kind
of state and uh and rag is something
that's actually being used for
there's like the end result is a bunch
of very relevant information, right? And
the source is a bunch of too much
information. So there has to be multiple
stages. I think right now what seems to
be uh useful is kind of similar to the
old recommendation system as well is you
use some weaker models to do a course
ranking and then you get a sufficient
amount of candidates and then you do a
fine fine grain ranking. Now normally
course ranking is using keywords vector
embedding and things like that and then
you use you know like LLM and concept
window because it actually understands
things much better. The first step is
optimizing on cost and the second step
is op optimizing on accuracy and and the
balance in between is kind of something
that people tune quite a bit in
different applications. I think like the
the concrete question was when we're
basically looking at the Berkeley
website and then we use Elmo to
summarize it and do question answering
uh where does the knowledge come from?
Is it that the model already learned uh
that Berkeley was founded in 1868 or is
it infer inence from the uh from the uh
from the context itself? Right? Um
this is kind of like a question that's
that kind of like like like
bothers me quite a bit as well. mainly
because I think in like in theory the
the model should be should be basically
only learning general practices or logic
from the training data and it should
rely on the facts that are in the text
right but I mean the boundary is kind of
unclear because you know like
there's nowhere in the text that will
basically say like a dog is an animal
because we think that that's common
knowledge but what is the boundary
between common knowledge and specific
knowledge right and I think that comes
quite a lot with like uh uh that's one
of the reason that like hallucination
and things are just causing big issues
today. Um and I think that's why you
know like rag and uh an efficient well
like an effective data search and and uh
and data source is super important
especially in more like enterprise and
vertical applications because general
search is more about common knowledge
but then verticalized search like
enterprise search is more about
summarizing reading informations and
that's why I think tying back to the
last question I think rack and accurate
data processing pipelines is super
important quite a lot of orchestration
abstractions on in the general compute
days and in AI days as well right why is
it continuing to be an important topic
and what are the uh what are what are
factors that made it hard I guess that's
the question right
let me basically try to so so so so to
find out question basically uh there is
promise seven eight years ago about
basically an abstraction layer that will
allow people to very easily do you like
a cloud dev environment um for like for
micro cloud and things like that and why
is it still not so right so I think I
can basically answer it from two
perspectives one is the implicit
difficulty in training and second is the
implicit difficulty in uh in data and in
training in the past a lot of the cloud
practices are basically having the
assumption that machines are all
abstracted away as replaceable
individual um virtual machines and their
exact physical location in the racks or
in the data center does not matter that
much because the workloads on top of
there is not tightly integrated and
today what we found is that for AI
training locality actually matters a lot
when we're actually requesting four
machines to train a distributed training
job we better find these machines that
are actually on the same rack attached
to the same switch. So the conventional
cloud practice of abstracting things
away using VM and Kubernetes and things
like that actually doesn't really work
that well in AI compute and that changes
a lot of the narratives and like
infrastructure pieces and things like
that. The other things when we talk
about um uh data um data locality is
still quite important because if I like
want to launch a machine somewhere it's
really easy to just like install PyTorch
but if I have you know a pabyte of data
that I need to basically install onto
that provider's storage that's connected
to that machine then it becomes very
fragmented some of the uh some of the um
so so for the C providers they normally
have elastic block storage elastic file
systems. They have object store and
things like that. In a neo cloud or
conventional slurm environment, we
normally has good old school uh NFS,
luster FS and other type of parallel FS
and providing an abstraction that would
uh span across all these different type
of storage and also creating a clean
data pipeline to efficiently pull data
into that becomes a challenge and I
think snow uh actually not snowflake sky
pilot basically tries to abstract some
of those away but essentially the data
movement bottleneck still is and making
it not as as simple as just launching a
micros service and those kind of things
makes infra evolution a little bit slow
that I kind of learned in retrospective
like doing the startup was uh was that
and by the way I mean brilliant
co-founders and things like that we've
had a really good run so it's not like a
failure story but one thing we found is
that as technical people we've often
been thinking about things in an
efficiencydriven or basically in an
inside outdriven kind of approach by
basically saying how do we actually
craft a very nice product that people
will be able to use. That actually led
us to build really nice platforms like
that that our customers like. Um but at
the same time, one thing that we've been
learning from the last two years is that
getting awareness out there is actually
super important and it's at least as
important as building a product. And
that's why there's all kinds of startup
showcases and things like that. And
sometimes you feel that all those CEOs
are just going out there like clowns
basically like like like like in a
blatantly bluffing way talking about how
excited and how good the products are,
things like that. Having done a startup,
I kind of like start understanding those
kind of things better because just like
the research paper says, attention is
all you need and um only by driving
attention and grabbing the customers and
basically efficiently using the customer
feedback to very quickly iterate on the
products because this is like way more
important than ever before and then do
this this flywheel. Uh can a startup be
successful? But thinking like we're kind
of joking that if we were if we were to
do leptin around again not saying it's
still very successful and happy but if
we were to do it again we will be
bullshitting more in a respectful manner
kind like observing a great engineers
and great scientists and over the years
and one thing I kind of find myself
being very useful and to brag a little
bit is that I kind of learned to to to
speak the languages both sides and that
helped quite a lot because researchers
see me as their friends uh because I can
actually like talk papers talk about
math and things like that and understand
that they do not really want to deal
with infra and uh and engineers see me
as a friend as well because they see
that I've done you know CIS admin in the
past and I acknowledge the inherent
difficulty of fixing machines and for
better or worse in in many places
there's a bit of professional hatred
between engineers and researchers
because they don't go headtohead and I
kind of feel action like being able to
be in the middle and helping smoothen
the message actually could help quite a
lot and then in the end people are like
oh yeah we're actually talking about the
same thing but just with like slightly
different priorities and things and uh a
good thing is both researchers and
engineers are very mathematics and
logics driven so I think I think it uh
it's uh it's something that that like if
there is a smooth conversation enabled
across the spectrum things get much
better than uh than when it's not. So
the question is basically like in this
area where models are becoming more and
more expensive to train and how does if
one wants to do a startup what might be
places of uh of like of of its unique
value right so um I might have a overly
biased view of that uh my feeling is
that basically like training yet another
foundational model um has space but
that's unless you have you know like a
very strong financial backend and you
have a team of really talented
researchers and at the same time I think
there's quite a lot of the application
areas that yet to that are yet to be
solved especially in the enterprise
service land and over there I think you
know like large companies and even open
AI and folks will not have enough focus
onto that because they have a wider
problem to solve and as a result the
startup will be able to combine the
domain knowledge and the nent or
basically the new techniques like things
and combine it to solve a vertical area
really Well and uh and that's the place
where you know like I think startups
will be running much better much faster
than the big companies and create
differentiated value. So if I may uh I
can summarize it as basically like what
is the what is the balance between you
know like scaling and centralization
versus more needed edge compute
distributed compute and efficient
compute on the other side right and
today we're talking quite a lot about
you know like huge clusters for train
and inference but then there are
robotics and you know like uh like say
like mobile phone intelligence and
things like that on the other hand so I
think this is basically the balance
between exploration and exploitation um
in the sense that you like when we are
still shooting for the best model, we
were like we don't care too much about
cost. We want to land people onto the
moon or Mars. So burning a bit more fuel
doesn't matter that much. And that's
basically the trend that we are seeing
in the last two years. Uh there is this
path of exploitation or more efficient
models happening for sure especially in
the robotics land mainly because you
know like when it comes to inference it
indeed is like that. This also kind of
like has an this is also kind of
similarly happening in the cloud land
where uh the um uh the the uh the telos
the telecom companies and also like the
CDN companies like Cloudflare are
basically thinking how can we actually
deploy AI comput capabilities on the
edge node on the pop of entrance
basically pop entrances like that right
and um and over there you may be able to
see a more distributed computation
resources closer to the closer to
basically where the computation is
needed right and um and I think that's
basically like when that's where people
are looking into more efficient models
efficient comput and things like that uh
still Nathan but there are still uh but
there are already a few companies who
are trying to do that so uh for example
um
uh so so son who is basically like build
student and now teaching at MIT and one
of their uh grad students were actually
starting a company called Ien AI AI lab
uh which is proposing in the idea of if
I remember correctly AEI artificial
efficient intelligence basically saying
we want to basically build models that
actually can run on you know um resource
constrained platforms like a robot or
phone um it hasn't been I would
basically say it hasn't been the the
main interest in the last two years
because there's so much topline to be uh
to be to be reached but uh as we look at
look more and more into the application
areas I'm sure that they will become
ever more important It's interesting. Um
the biggest
>> Thanks. Um
last question basically. So I think the
question was uh could you share the
biggest technical problem that we
encountered in the in the in the leptton
days right and interesting I've got
really great co-founders. So technically
it wasn't really too much of a trouble.
So one of our co-founder is the creator
of etc which is the fundamental database
on Kubernetes. So I relied to him on uh
on all kinds of like Kubernetes infra.
Uh the biggest slightly related to
technology kind of challenge that we had
back at back back at not Berkeley Leon
days was actually supply chain
management. Uh because there's such a
shortage of GPUs and GPUs are such an
arbitrage market we found ourselves to
spend quite a lot of time procuring GPUs
and negotiating contracts and
negotiating pricing terms. Can we do a
six months term? Can we do a three
months term? Can we do a committed
spending but with flexible scale up and
down over a period of time and things
like that. Uh that consumed quite a lot
of you know like time of hours and
interestingly when I was talking to um a
lot of the fellow startup founders those
were the problems that they were facing
as well. So I really hope that basically
like in the next few well in next months
or years there could be a more fluid
marketplace where we can where where
where where the startup founders and
enterprises can actually go and find
efficient computation resources in a
multicloud or across the globe so that
they can focus on building models and
applications and rather than basically
doing infra ops which has been the
30-year-old topic. That was one of the
big problems that we encountered.
Thanks.